[metal rattling]
[worker straining, groaning]
Buddy, I'm gonna have to charge you
double for that.
And if it turns out you're carrying tools,
it's triple...
That should more than cover it.
Appreciate the ride, Ossie.
Chad, Jo. You're both looking well.
I'm guessing she's expecting me.
[breathing heavily]
Bernard.
Camille.
What do you want?
[The Algorithm] Bernard Holland.
Why are you here?
I know drugs are in the water,
and that you have Juliette.
I'm here to ask for her release.
And for you to turn off the vitamin D+.
And why would I do that?
Because in return I'm giving you the gift
of narrative, which you need right now.
Word is spreading out of Mechanical
that you brainwashed Juliette.
I can save you from a rebellion.
Is that true?
[The Algorithm] Social harmony
remains well below Mayor Jahns's tenure.
Even below Mr. Holland's brief term.
People are easily manipulated.
All they need is someone worse,
and I will be that person for you.
You tell them that I killed Meadows.
You can also say that I ordered
the deaths of Jahns and Marnes,
and that I lied
about Juliette wanting to go out.
Blame the unrest
of the past few months on me.
None of it would be a lie.
I was following orders, just like you are.
And what happens after that?
Rehabilitate me to show
what a merciful leader you are...
far more than I ever was.
Then I will live my days out quietly.
Go ahead. Run the numbers.
[The Algorithm]
The difference in outcomes is negligible.
On the other hand,
if we present the narrative
you've suggested,
then send you outside to clean,
and maintain the original plan
with Juliette Nichols and the vitamin D+,
the Silo actually benefits.
That can't be right.
You're missing something.
People want redemption stories.
Redemption is the commonality in all
the great myths, the major religions.
[The Algorithm]
Not only have you miscalculated,
you have also failed to realize
that you have no leverage.
You are already in custody,
and you remain deeply unpopular
with 89% of the population.
You're gonna take everything from me
after I've given my life to you?
- [The Algorithm] Goodbye, Bernard.
- You're not an omniscient, are you?
If you were actually omniscient,
you wouldn't have led us here
to begin with.
You wouldn't need to erase
everyone's memories or kill so many.
You don't know
much more than I do, do you?
[The Algorithm] Goodbye, Bernard.
Did that turn out the way you expected?
Yes.
It's been the same voice
for the entire time I served.
But I've never heard it end
a conversation like that. Have you?
- No, but I also don't provoke it.
- Exactly.
It wanted to stop talking
because of annoyance, frustration, anger.
Rather unmachine-like characteristics,
wouldn't you say?
One time, not long ago... it was strange.
It consoled me.
And you wondered whether it was human.
How would that be possible?
Someone whose voice
hasn't changed all these years
and is always available to talk.
Same voice.
Perhaps not the same person.
I know one thing about a person.
A person can be defeated.
[Camille] Good morning, citizens.
I have important news.
Former interim mayor and head of IT,
Bernard Holland, has been found alive.
[citizens murmuring, clamoring]
For all his crimes against the Silo,
he has been sentenced
by the judge to clean at noon today.
Please make plans to attend the viewing
in the nearest cafeteria.
As always,
be courteous and safe on the stairs.
Thank you.
[Hank] Sheriff!
[sighs]
- Did you hear that?
- Yeah.
Then you know I can't stay.
I just need 5 minutes.
[on radio]
Deputy Jerry for Sheriff Billings.
Don't answer that. Not yet, please.
I had that door reinforced.
So whatever you're doing, just...
you should save your energy.
But if we hit the joints at the same time,
maybe we can weaken the hinges, right?
Even if you got out,
that hallway is full of raiders.
Okay, okay. So, that's it?
Well, the only way it ends differently
is if my wife stops taking orders
from that fucking screen.
I don't even know who she is right now.
[sighs]
[Martha] So, there's so much
we have to tell you,
and we will,
but since your time is limited,
I'm gonna start
with where we are this morning.
[sighs] Bernard Holland offered himself up
to clean as a distraction.
For what?
I'll come to that.
Knox tells me
we can only do what we need to do
if we use something that you discovered.
- You told her?
- No.
Even my own wife wouldn't tell me.
Not my call.
And I didn't tell Shirl.
Because... [scoffs]
...this is such a big violation of the Pact.
You have to be the one to show them.
What is it you want me to do?
Well, to start, we have to get
into water filtration on 55.
[door opens]
Nichols, up.
- She's still mayor, Chad.
- Get up.
It's okay. I'm going.
[whispers] It's okay.
[Chad] Hold it there. Hands.
[door closes]
[Knox, Paul strain, grunt]
Go ahead. We've already seen it.
[Teddy] What the fuck?
I heard you weren't much of a drinker,
so I had these portered down
from your office.
I didn't think you'd mind.
Sure.
Do you--
Some water then?
So why am I here?
Sit.
[inhales sharply]
[exhales deeply]
Did your friends tell you
what happened during the rebellion?
I got the highlights.
Did they tell you Bernard tried
to starve them out?
Stopped all food deliveries
to the Down Deep?
Even had one of the kitchen workers
poison the pantry.
I helped the rebels move the barricade up
ten floors so they'd have a farm.
Your friends would have died,
and their rebellion would have
been over if it wasn't for me.
And then they only won
because Robert and I got the support
of the sheriff's deputies.
Well, I'm sure you had your reasons.
Bernard couldn't be trusted anymore.
So I went against my orders,
against the Pact, to do what was right.
[chuckles]
[smacks lips] I know Bernard didn't die.
In fact, we have him now.
He's going out to clean at noon today.
You will preside as mayor.
Oh, he turned himself in.
And I presume he was
hiding down with your friends?
Is that why I'm here?
You want me to confirm that?
No, not at all.
No, I-I asked you here
because I want us to work together.
[chuckles] I think, um,
I'll take one of those now.
[chuckles]
Look, what's happening with the water
is an extreme measure,
but I don't have
any other choice at this point.
People know too much.
Look,
they're starting to ask questions,
in large part because of you.
Questions that can,
and will, get us killed.
[sniffles] Fucking hell. People like that?
After half a glass, you don't really care.
You put drugs in the water.
Do you have any idea
what that's going to lead to when--
It will no doubt be painful,
as it was 140 years ago.
No, the forgetting won't be painful.
The consequences are.
Hundreds of people jumped off the stairs.
Children starved to death
'cause their parents forgot to feed them.
Okay, I know.
And this is where you come in.
You and a person from each department.
Wow.
'Cause you need us to train everyone
to function as a society again,
is that it?
And then what?
You and the other representatives
will need to forget as well.
Right.
But not... not you.
Someone has to ensure
the transition is successful.
Of course.
And why wouldn't that be you, Camille?
Fuck you.
I'll have my memories, yeah.
But I'll be alone in that.
- Oh.
- Each day-- Look at me.
Each day until everything is reset,
I'll have to remind my son who I am
and hope he believes me.
Or that there's enough of him left
to remember.
[on radio] Emerson for Camille Sims.
Yes, what... what is it?
A lot of people are heading up.
Yeah, we're expecting that, Emerson.
Everyone wants to see Bernard Holland die.
No, I think it's something else.
There's a couple hundred following the two
from Mechanical who led the rebellion.
And another group not moving,
ten levels up on 55.
Do not let them get to water filtration.
Copy that.
[citizens clamoring]
[chanting] Let us through! Let us through!
Let us through!
Hey! Hey!
You know what's in the water.
Step aside and none of your people
have to end up in Medical.
Go home.
You fuck this up
and I will throw every single one
of your friends over the side.
They wanna wipe our memories.
That goes for you too.
Ready your weapons!
Whoa, whoa, whoa, whoa.
Hey, hey!
Let's do this another day.
We've made our point.
No! Let us through!
[citizens chanting] Let us through!
Let us through! Let us through.
[Juliette] Hey! Stop!
Just put your weapons down. Now.
Just... go home.
They put drugs in the water.
It's not true.
It's vitamin D.
Just go home.
Go.
You heard her. Let's go. Let's go.
Well done.
Your friends get to live another day.
Watch her.
[sighs] Good job holding the line.
Out of precaution, I need you all
to stay here until after the cleaning.
Wait.
Is it true?
About the water.
Absolutely not.
No, it's just another
Down Deep conspiracy theory.
This is amazing.
Feels like my stomach's in my ass.
Wait. You never rode this?
- No.
- [elevator rattles]
[laughs]
Yeah, and I was shit-faced
when I designed it.
- [chuckles]
- [sighs] Yeah, fantastic.
People obey you
even when they don't agree.
That will be useful in the transition.
Yeah, I'm not gonna help you.
And even if I did,
you'd kill me anyway, so...
- You're right.
- So that's your plan?
You're just gonna get rid
of anyone who helps you?
No, just you.
You're still pissed off
I went into your home.
I let you go, remember?
No.
I didn't remember, but I do now.
Even if we take your memories again,
I have no doubt you and I would still find
our way back to this exact same moment
- because you don't ever quit.
- [inhales deeply]
Check her left sleeve.
So, yes, you'll die.
Everyone else gets to live.
I'll even make sure
you're remembered as a hero.
Fuck you.
Get her ready for the cleaning.
Bring my husband to our apartment.
[citizens chattering]
[grunts]
Shirl, this is...
I forget what he goes by now.
Gone back to Gus.
Who's this?
Shirley. I've heard about you.
Oh, yeah?
Whatever you heard from him...
[chuckles] ...he's not wrong.
Come on. Let's go.
I know you're upset with me
for keeping Bernard alive.
It wasn't an easy choice.
Camille, I love you more than you know.
But I also love our son.
And you were asking me
to go along with taking his memories.
Who will he be after that?
Who would we be?
I have no regrets.
You talk about protecting our son,
but you and Bernard
put every single person at risk.
Before long all Anthony will know
about you is what I tell him.
Bring him up in 15 minutes.
I'm not taking a chance.
You'll go out without a suit.
You can't do that.
You know that's against the Pact.
It's actually not.
And a suit wouldn't change much anyway.
[Chad] Ma'am, the sheriff is here.
Did you actually say you wanna go out
or did some asshole pretend to hear it?
[chuckles]
- You've drawn a record-size crowd.
- [chuckles]
- I said that to you, didn't I?
- Yeah.
[inhales deeply] In my case,
it's the perk of being hated by every man,
woman, child, and sanctioned pet.
Why did you turn yourself in?
[whispers] To give Walker
and your friends a distraction.
No, no, no, no, no, no.
Bernard. Camille forced me
to send Knox and Shirley away.
She had guns pointed at them.
She was gonna kill them.
I had no choice. It... It didn't work.
But it's not over.
You're being sent out to die.
- Juliette.
- No. I'm still the mayor.
Camille... she wants me to help her...
- Stop--
- ...once the drugs set in, right?
So she wants me to be there.
She wants me to make a deal with her.
- And I said no. But maybe I can--
- Stop! Please.
- You want to keep fighting?
- Yeah.
Good. Because I still am.
How is this fighting?
[whispers] All eyes will be on me.
Three months ago, your friends
pulled off a rebellion in your name.
Since then I've seen who they are,
what they can do.
I was able to be a part of it.
I've never had that in my life.
The power that your people have.
What they're capable of...
given an opportunity, given a chance.
My death is a chance.
They won't waste it.
Trust them.
It's not about not trusting them.
[breathes shakily]
But I could still find a way.
What choice do we have?
I don't--
The most important thing
I can leave you with is this...
that voice in the wall...
I always thought it was a machine.
An entity of some kind.
A higher intelligence.
It's not.
Somewhere in Silo 1 is a person.
Flesh and blood.
No different or better than you or me.
A person deciding our fates.
[gasps]
Turns out, after all this,
the wizard is nothing more
than a man behind a curtain.
And if that man
were in this room right now,
I'd kill him with my bare hands.
But I won't get that chance.
But you can stop them, Juliette.
You are the one their numbers missed.
I know you don't want to be a leader,
so you don't see this.
But you are more than a disrupter.
You are a unifier.
Your team proves that.
They believe in you.
And I believe in you. All of you.
And there's one last thing on my mind.
All the questions I won't see answered.
They all come down to just one question.
[door opens]
Let's go.
[Paul] We do not know why we are here.
We do not know who built the Silo.
We do not know why everything
outside the Silo is as it is.
We do not know
when it will be safe to go outside.
We only know that day is not this day.
Do you have any last words?
[inhales deeply]
[citizens chattering]
Why isn't he wearing a suit?
[breathing heavily]
[grunting]
[sniffs, coughs]
[panting]
[exhales deeply]
You know Bernard said that, um,
everything that we don't know
about the silos
can be answered in one question.
And I think it's as simple as, "Why?"
We keep asking the same questions
over and over again.
Why were the silos built?
Why do people have to go into them?
Why... Why couldn't the silos communicate
with each other, right?
And if the Founders cared so fucking much,
why would they put in a Safeguard
to be able to kill us?
Maybe we aren't meant to know the answers.
Why?
- [rumbling]
- [clattering]
[citizens shouting, exclaiming]
Everybody... Everybody stay calm.
We'll figure out what's going on.
Hey! Stay calm. You're safer here.
Take care of each other.
We're gonna figure it out.
You planned this.
No, I was in custody all day.
[Ed] Fire in the hole.
[explosion]
- [loud rumbling]
- [citizens screaming]
[Paul] Hey, hey. No, no. Don't leave.
Don't leave. Hey, listen to me.
Stay, stay.
The mines.
You...
Fuck.
[Paul] Stay calm! All right?
Your friends may have just killed us all.
Move! Out of the way!
[heartbeat thumping on ultrasound]
[doctor] There's that beautiful head.
[Daniel] There she is.
- [Helen chuckles]
- [doctor] Everything looks healthy.
- You okay, there, chief?
- Yeah.
[sighs] It's just feeling so real now.
Now? Real... Did-Did you hear? Real now?
[chuckles] You give him
the constant peeing,
and the back pain
and leg cramps and swelling.
If I could, half the world would love me
- and the other half would hate me.
- [Helen] Right.
- [Helen chuckles]
- Um... [chuckles] So can she fly?
You're almost at the cutoff point,
but this weekend should be fine.
Where are you off to?
Atlanta.
[chuckling] The Stensen thing?
You won a golden ticket
to the chocolate factory? [chuckles]
I had a few friends that applied for that
but couldn't get it.
Do you know him?
- We met him once.
- Hi?
We met him. We did.
Did you, uh, have to sign NDAs?
I mean, he's famous
for making people sign NDAs.
[Helen] Charlotte?
- Hey.
- [Charlotte] Hey. Oh, my God.
You're huge.
- [laughs]
Is that not what I'm supposed to say?
- Only if I wasn't huge. Hi.
- [chuckles] Hi.
- [Charlotte] Oh. Hey.
- Hey.
[Charlotte] Thanks for making the trip.
- Ah! There you are. Oh, you look great.
- [Helen] Hey. [chuckles]
- Thank you. Hi.
- Oh! Oh, it's so nice to see you.
Hey. Hey.
Well, I hope you guys like takeout.
Someone forgot to defrost the chicken.
You evil fucker.
- I did not say who that someone was.
- Okay.
- For you.
- Ah, thank you. That's so kind.
Come on in. Come on.
[Anna laughs] Oh.
Okay. How are the bridges in Portland?
[Daniel] They're keeping me busy.
We're looking to retrofit the Burnside,
which is this-this beautiful
old Bascule bridge from 19--
- [snores]
- Such an asshole.
- Such a dick. Unbelievable. [laughs]
- [Anna] Char, stop.
[laughing]
And you? Driving a drone
for a trillionaire? How's that?
It's a job.
How is The Oregonian?
[sighs] Understaffed, budget cuts,
dwindling subscriptions.
The... The usual.
And have you guys picked out a name yet?
- [Helen gasps]
- [Anna] Aw...
[Charlotte] We've been wondering. Come on.
[sighs] Um... Daniel Keene II.
- [groans] Shut up. Wow.
- Come on.
- [Helen] Do you like it? [laughs]
- [Charlotte] Shut up.
- [Anna] Oh, Jesus.
- [Charlotte] Wow.
How about you two? Do you have any plans?
Oh.
Either way,
you both look really, really happy.
- Yeah. We are.
- [Charlotte chuckles] Mmm.
[Daniel] Yeah.
I wish Mom and Dad could see you.
If they were alive right now...
Hmm.
They'd be clawing frantically to get out.
...to get out of their coffins.
- [groans] God.
- [groans] It's a sickness. It's so dark.
- Yeah. [chuckles]
- But I'm still... I'm glad you came.
We, uh, almost didn't.
[Anna] Really?
Daniel thinks your mom is still mad at us.
- [Daniel] Oh, that is not... Uh, is she?
- Oh...
You know, if she asks to speak with you,
it usually means
she wants to bury the hatchet. Right?
- [Daniel sighs]
- [Charlotte laughs] Sure. Yeah.
[Anna laughs] We'll never know.
How is everything?
Are... you guys ready for the big unveiling?
Yeah, the light's
finally at the end of the tunnel.
Except it's not daylight, it's a train!
[laughs]
[chuckles]
- Oh, wait. No, no, I'm sorry.
- No, no, it's okay. [chuckles]
No, tomorrow's gonna be amazing.
Your mom is gonna be thrilled.
And when it's all over,
we can finally go on a real honeymoon.
You get one extra museum
'cause I was mean.
Hmm. Could we go back like 30 seconds?
Yes.
- [Anna] Hmm.
- You said I'm sorry.
Oh, very rare. [chuckles]
- I've never heard that.
- I never hear any apology.
- I mean, so rude.
- [Anna] She doesn't do it ever.
- Rare?
- I haven't seen that before.
- [Anna] It is.
- Right. Well, I'm not gonna apologize
when I shove this down your throat.
- I can do it. I'll do it.
- Take it. Take it.
- [Helen] No.
- [Daniel] No problem.
[Charlotte] They're hot.
- [chuckles]
- [Charlotte] Great. [laughs]
- [coughing]
- Ah. There it is.
[water running]
Oh, hey, hey, hey.
I'll do the rest. I'll do it.
Keene family rule.
Whoever makes dinner
gets the rest of the night off.
I drove to get takeout. Just let me.
- You're afraid I'm gonna do it wrong?
- [laughs]
- Stepping away.
- Thank you.
All right.
I'm sorry we didn't make it back
when you were sick.
You sent enough flowers
to fill three funeral homes, so...
Oh, God. That's not what we...
Look, Helen was newly pregnant
and dealing with her dad.
Yeah. I could've come.
I don't... I don't know.
Left her alone?
Even Char doesn't think
you're that much of an asshole. [laughs]
[Anna clears throat]
Fought it before, fought it again.
And I had Char with me, and my mother,
and... and... and Henry. [chuckles]
Oh, well, if Henry was there.
I have known Henry
since I was 12 years old.
He performs a very important service.
He, um, comes in after my mother visits
and, like,
sweeps up the emotional debris.
[laughs]
Anyway, I'm fine now.
I'm grateful actually.
For Charlotte, I mean, not the cancer.
Fuck cancer.
Yeah. [chuckles]
- [music on radio playing]
- [Helen, Charlotte laugh]
Hmm. You know, the day we were married,
I didn't think I could love her more.
And then this winter...
Oof. [chuckles]
And you know, it wasn't even
that she took care of me, which she did.
It was that, um...
[clicks tongue]
So, when I was getting treatment,
she would go to the floor below
and see the kids in the chairs.
She's got some rough edges, your sister,
the Navy thing and all that.
- Oh, really.
- [chuckles] She would, like...
she would, like, try and rein it in,
but she would just wind up swearing
like a sailor.
"Fuck cancer
and fuck the horse it rode in on."
And the kids just, like, loved it.
[both laugh]
And their parents loved it.
And then... [groans]
Yeah, that's when I knew.
It was just, like...
She is one tough lady, you know.
But, man, she's kind. She's so kind.
[breathes shakily]
It's wild. We're actually letting people
into the silos tomorrow.
And by people, you know,
I mean civilian swine, like you.
Oh, thank you. Got it. [chuckles]
I'm just glad
I finally get to talk about it.
Yeah, I know. Those NDAs suck.
Sorry we couldn't tell you much.
It's fine.
Besides, signing those NDAs got us
the nicest home in West Slope.
- Got us this Craftsman in Morningside.
- Hmm.
It's been nuts... last six months.
The second
Anna's cancer treatment was done,
I mean,
she was back to all silos all the time.
Have you heard of the Pact?
- Mm-mmm.
- Oh, my God. Okay.
So it's some crazy shit
she and Dr. C wrote.
- Who?
- Oh, Victor.
- Right.
- So, it is a book of rules
about how to live underground
for 500 years without killing each other.
- 500 years?
- I know. I said it was crazy.
So is the fact that Stensen got
the silos operational in three years
and, I mean, well,
people are living there right now.
Not that I'm complaining.
Anna and me, we get to work together
and come back to this every night.
Kind of reminds me
of where Dan and I grew up.
You remember that?
I think so.
Sometimes it kind of feels
like someone else's story, but, um...
Yeah, it's good enough.
Your husband wants to go.
Did he say it's past my bedtime?
- He did. [laughs]
- Congressman.
- [laughs]
- [grunts]
[Charlotte] Mmm.
Do you have time for breakfast tomorrow?
Sure.
I-I don't know.
We-We might have to go over early.
Oh, I thought everything was figured out.
If you get, um, pecan sticky buns
from Star Market,
I'll do bacon and eggs.
- Sounds like a plan.
- [Charlotte] Okay.
- Good night.
- [Anna] Good night.
What are you?
Eighteen.
- I'm one.
- [chime sounds]
- [PA announcer] If you need assistance...
- One.
...see any representative
in a yellow jacket.
[Helen] This way.
I'll walk ya.
[representative] Daniel, Helen.
- [Helen] Hey.
- [Daniel] Henry.
- It's been a long time.
- [Henry] Congratulations.
- [Helen chuckles]
- You both are glowing.
Well, you are. I was just being inclusive.
- [Daniel chuckles]
- Right. Thank you, Henry. [chuckles]
We weren't sure you were gonna make it.
No, I had to see how it all turned out.
My advice is don't take the full tour.
It's a lot of stairs and no elevators.
I heard a rumor about that.
Something about people
getting enough exercise.
- Not my department.
- [Daniel chuckles]
So, hey, can I borrow Daniel?
The senator wants a word with him.
I'd love to see Charlotte.
She's at Silo 1
with Anna and the senators.
- Well, can Helen come?
- Well...
Uh, it's a pretty long walk.
- Yeah, no, uh...
- Yeah?
...you go see Charlotte.
I... [chuckles] I wanna take the tour.
- [Henry] They're gonna feed you in there.
- Great.
And when you're done,
come on over to Silo 1.
- And the senator's gonna make a speech.
- [inhales sharply]
[laughing] I know. I know, um,
she swears it's gonna be short.
- There's music and fireworks later, so...
- Okay.
I'm gonna talk to the senator
and come find you.
- [Helen] Okay.
- Okay.
Bye.
[chimes sounds]
[PA announcer]
Silo tour will begin shortly.
[guide] If you were told
to come to Silo 18,
uh, then you're in the right place.
Uh, I'm Everett.
I'm one of your tour guides for today.
- Oh, Samantha.
- Yes?
Uh, you're assigned to 17,
which is just over there.
- Oh. Right.
- Mm-hmm.
Sorry. [chuckles]
How did you know my name?
Augmented reality glasses.
They, uh... They pull up all of your info
from the RFID in your badge. [chuckles]
Uh, what if we're using
someone else's badge?
Well, Helen, these also come
with facial recognition.
Uh, Rachel will take the next 20 people.
But, uh, if you're one of the ones
I greeted then follow me.
[Rachel] All right. My group, over here.
[Helen] Where are you from, Everett?
- Oh, um, Hoddesdon.
- Hoddesdon?
Well, um... it's a small town
just outside of London
that even Londoners have never heard of.
[attendees chattering]
- [chime sounds]
- [camera shutter clicks]
[PA announcer] A reminder to our guests:
Please ensure you visit
- the correct silo number...
- [camera shutter clicks]
...as shown on your identification badge.
[camera shutter clicks]
Daniel.
- Victor. Hi. Hey. [chuckles]
- Daniel.
- How are you?
- Hi.
Victor, the senator wants to talk to him.
- I'll get him there. Yeah.
- Okay. Thank you.
Charlotte tells me you're gonna be a dad.
Yeah, I'm terrified. [laughs]
Congrats. No, you're gonna be great.
- Thank you. I'll certainly try.
- Yeah.
Pretty impressive, huh?
It's more than I imagined.
Yeah, trying to figure out
how we pulled it off?
Maybe you're wondering...
what it would've been like
if you said yes.
I made the right choice.
Of course you did.
But it is
one of the biggest engineering projects
in the history of the world.
Nothing wrong with thinking
about the road not taken.
[Daniel] Mm-hmm.
We all do.
You know, for what it's worth,
could've used you.
You had plenty of great engineers.
Sure. But I always felt
that you had a gift
for seeing things other people missed.
I gotta say, I was a little surprised
when I heard
you were still on the project.
I thought, you know,
a bunch of holes in the ground
wouldn't exactly require your skills.
You know, I-I thought the same thing.
But the more I was here
working with Charlotte,
the more I realized that, you know,
if these silos were ever to be used,
it would
be after a massive traumatic event,
and a lot of people would need help.
I... The more you dive
into this whole project, the more you...
the more you see how much there is to do
when it comes to managing mass trauma.
Like the Pact.
[chuckles] You heard about the Pact.
[chuckles] Charlotte told you, right?
- Yeah.
You and Anna writing a book about
how to live together for 500 years.
No. To be honest, AI wrote it.
We just did some editing.
And you know, hopefully, we'll never have
to find out if we did a good job.
[Daniel scoffs]
[Everett] Millions of people
from all around the world
applied to join the project.
And, uh, Dr. Stensen made it his goal
to have at least two people
from every country on Earth.
Two by two?
This really is Stensen's Ark, isn't it?
Okay.
This Silo was built to withstand
a 30 megaton nuclear explosion
as close as two miles.
Uh, these two big sliding doors each weigh
25 tons
and can keep out particles
as small as 50 nanometers.
Okay, Ms. Helen?
How much did each Silo end up costing?
Dr. Stensen plans
on releasing official figures soon.
Are you one of the people who's
been living in here for the past year?
Just under a year, but yes. Yes, I am.
And you haven't gone insane?
Okay, well, this is it, folks.
You are about to enter a Silo.
- [clapping]
- [laughing] Yes.
Uh, and I can guarantee you one thing...
whatever it is
you think you are gonna see,
you're not prepared.
Um, so follow me,
uh, mind your step, and, um, yeah...
Oh, Helen, at the risk of sounding
overly protective, would you take my arm?
Okay. Thank you.
It's this way.
[person mumbling on mic]
You gotta show your badge.
- ["Here Comes the Flood" playing]
- [person] One, two.
- Hey, fellas.
- [Daniel] Hi, how you doing?
Testing. Check. Let's go.
♪ When the night shows
The signals grow on radios ♪
♪ All the strange things
They come and go as early warnings ♪
♪ Stranded starfish have
No place to hide ♪
♪ Still waiting
For the swollen Easter tide ♪
♪ There's no point in direction ♪
♪ We cannot even choose a side ♪
- Is that Peter Gabriel? [chuckles]
- [chuckles] Yeah. Yeah.
♪ Here comes the flood ♪
♪ We will say goodbye to flesh and blood ♪
How much did that cost?
Nothing. He and his family wanted
to see inside a silo
- just like everybody else in the world.
- Which silo?
I think they're in 17. It's the best one.
They're not all the same?
[chuckles] No, they are.
[laughs] It's a Silo joke.
- Never mind. Come on.
- Right. [chuckles]
♪ Dreamers, you're running dry ♪
That'll do. Thanks. [clears throat]
[applause]
Oh, but that was fabulous.
- Thank you.
- Thank you, my friend. Oh, it was great.
Now, would you like to see Silo 17
before your performance tonight?
Daniel Keene,
- you are a sight for these poor old eyes.
- [chuckles]
Being out of Washington looks good on you.
Oh. Well, you look good yourself, Senator.
- Hmm. Still a politician.
- [chuckles]
Now, tell me, why is it I'd hear from Anna
about you being in town,
but you never stopped in for tea?
I knew you were busy.
I didn't wanna interrupt.
Well, you were right about that.
It took a fuckton of work
to get this all up and running.
- [Daniel] I bet.
- There he is.
- I've got a bone to pick with you.
- Oh, yeah?
Really could've used you on this, man.
If we hadn't followed your suggestion
of 50 diggers,
we'd have been five years behind schedule.
- Mm-hmm.
- Could've used that brain of yours
on all the other problems we had.
[Thurman]
Per and I have to do a tech check.
Hey, will you stick around?
I-I wanna discuss something with you.
- Sure.
- [Thurman] Thank you.
[Anna] Daniel.
Hey.
I'm sorry about breakfast.
No, don't worry about it.
We'll do it tomorrow.
- Yeah, that'd be great.
- Everything okay?
Mm-hmm. Oh, yeah, yeah.
Just... they wanted us here early, so...
[Daniel] Sure.
Where's Charlotte?
You know, I don't know.
The last I saw, she was in the cafeteria
finishing off a mocha.
So I guess she'll be out soon.
[Thurman] Today, "my fellow Americans"
no longer seems adequate.
This project is meant
to safeguard all of us
regardless of color, creed or nationhood.
So today,
I say my fellow people, all people...
["Chopsticks" playing on keyboard]
Per? Hey, Per. Per.
You need to focus, okay?
This project is the pinnacle
of my long, and some might say
too long, career.
Anna, Anna.
Oh, um, not... not long enough.
Yeah, honey, you leave me
hanging like that, I'm dead.
- Okay?
- Won't happen again.
But the reason I'm so proud...
Let's speed this up...
The reason I'm so proud of this project is
a culmination of bipartisan cooperation,
American can-do, yada yada yada... Okay.
This is government
and industry working together
on a level not seen since World War II.
This applause will last,
I don't know, five, ten seconds.
I'll start back up the third time
I raise my hand, okay?
One, two, three... Now,
I'm not gonna take all the credit.
If we should thank anyone
for this magnificent undertaking,
it's this man right here.
A man whose genius
still exceeds his wealth.
Per Stensen. Just... Come on.
You don't want the applause dying
before you get here.
Uh, I know some people think
this whole endeavor is a statement
on how we've given up on the future,
but that couldn't be farther
from the truth.
This is a project of hope
and the human spirit.
[Thurman] Now, I know Per's already
dreaming up the next big thing,
building a spaceship to carry explorers
to the nearest inhabitable star system.
Are you gonna have any dough left, Per?
Now if that gets a laugh, just use it
to cover your cross back to the side.
- [phone buzzing]
- If it doesn't, stay put, all right?
Now, even if the silos are never needed,
and Lord hoping they won't be,
they will be continually occupied
as long as the many threats remain.
And they will be studied as prototypes
of sustainability and resource management.
They will be studied as prototypes
Hey, what the fuck, Jeff?
Come on. We gotta do better than ending
the most important speech of my life
with the words "resource management,"
right?
[Jeff] I cleared this with you yesterday.
[Thurman] No.
This goes here. [speaking indistinctly]
[Anna] You okay? What's going on?
- Daniel?
- Huh?
I'm just gonna... gonna take a second.
Okay.
[clears throat]
[attendees chattering]
[panting]
[groans, pants]
Hey, I'm getting a little, uh... uh...
I don't know... worried.
Can you call me as soon as you can?
[Henry] Daniel.
Hey, uh, give me a call when you can.
Daniel, you have to come back now.
- Where's 18?
- I'll take you there later.
[Daniel sighs]
[Rachel] I can guarantee you one thing,
no matter what it is you think
you're gonna see, you are not prepared.
Uh, ma'am?
Ma'am, it's time to head in for dinner.
Yeah, no. A hard pass.
[panting]
[Helen, distorted] Hey, where are you?
Uh, Silo 1. Top of the berm.
Yeah, can you get to that raised area
around your Silo?
- The signal might be better.
- Yeah, I'm almost there.
[pants] The Silo is so fucking weird.
It's so deep you can't see the bottom
and there really aren't
any fucking elevators.
- Where are you?
- Hel...
I can't--
I'm coming to 1, so just stay there.
No, no, no, no. No. I'm-I'm coming to 18.
You're at 18? I can't... I can't see you.
I'm coming to 18. Just stay there.
Okay, okay. I can hear you.
I can hear you.
I got a text from Charlotte.
But I don't know.
I don't think she wrote it.
Who wrote it then?
I-I don't know.
[Helen] I think I see you. Wave.
To your right. Look for the big red dot.
[sighs] Hey.
Hi, Congressman. [chuckles]
[explosion]
- [ringing]
- [Daniel, distorted gasps]
[panting]
[grunts]
[pants]
Daniel. [gasps]
Helen. Helen!
- No. No!
- There's no point.
[Daniel grunting] No!
[The Algorithm] Seek shelter in
the nearest Silo as quickly as possible.
- [grunting] Helen! Helen!
- [Henry] Daniel!
Helen! No!
We're trying to save your life.
- Fuck! Run!
- [grunts]